all right all right all right
so today we're gonna be talking again
about foundations of deep learning
that's me alfredo and you can find me on
twitter
on the handle alfcnz actually if you
check twitter you can find some
you could find some news about today's
lesson
since i posted online like yesterday
night
so the deal is always the same as soon
as you don't understand as
soon as i don't make sense since i
didn't sleep and i've been working on
this stuff for the last 30 hours
it's very likely i'm not gonna be making
much sense at some times
so every time something is not clear
just stop me
ask me anything because again if we keep
going
and you're not following then we are not
going anywhere okay
all right so today we're going to be
talking about inference
for latent variable energy-based models
ebns
for example the ellipse likewise
we have cover only inference only
inference in our first lab
today we're gonna be only covering
inference for energy based models
i will not say the word training ever
again
okay i'll try at least so today we're
gonna be talking about
inference what is this stuff and where
do we start
we're going to be starting from our
training examples
training training samples i said i
wasn't going to say this word
all right so let's see what kind of data
we're going to be working on and why we
need these energy based models
so we can think about our data why
bold y is uh it's been living
having two components y one y two
y one is gonna be this row one function
of x
which is going to be my input multiplied
by the cosine of theta
which is some you know angle we don't
know
plus some epsilon noise and then row 2
is going to be again a function of my
input x and then it's multiplied by a
sine
of this theta we have no axis plus some
uh noise epsilon
rho is a function that maps the input
one dimensional r into a r2 and so it's
mapping my
x into something that is this alpha x
plus beta
1 minus x for the first component and
the other is beta
times x plus alpha multiply 1 minus x
and and then everything is multiplied by
this exponential
of x so alpha and beta
are simply 1.5 and 2 so this is simply
the
equation for a ellipse but then if x
goes from zero to one as i show you here
you're gonna have that this is gonna be
drawing
some sort of horn that is exponentially
no in the profile
and then it starts as like something
like this and then eventually
like horizontal ellipse and eventually
end up as a vertical ellipse
okay x here is going to be sample from
the uniform distribution
similarly theta is also sampled from the
uniform distribution from 0 to 2 pi
epsilon instead is sampled from a normal
distribution
with mean 0 and then a standard
deviation of 1 over 20.
so again as you might have seen from
twitter
this stuff looks pretty cool and it
looks like
that but then since we have magic on
this side we can do this
and so you can see here how we're gonna
be having this exponential
uh side right this exponential envelope
we start with the uh ellipse that is
like vertical and then we end up with
this horizontal one
okay um
what we want to pay attention here
is that at a given specific location
x there is no
one y only right so we cannot really
train a neural net that is like a
vector to vector mapping because there
is no vector to map
well there is a bunch of vectors right
so given one
single input x there are many many many
possible
y's there is like a whole uh ellipse
right
uh per given x so we can't really use
normal uh feed forward neural net to do
this
uh similarly if we are just talking
about y's
given one value of y one i cannot even
tell
what is the other corresponding y two
because there are
always two almost always two values for
y two given one y one right
and so using vectors to vectors mapping
as we've been learning so far is not
quite
uh sufficient so today we're going to be
figuring out how to use these latent
variable energy-based models to deal
with this kind of
multimodal you know outcome
so to make things simple and make my
life easier
we're gonna do a few simplifications uh
the first one i'm gonna be removing the
input so there will be no input data
my model will not have input data
and this is like what anyhow i i fix my
x to zero so by fixing the x to zero i'm
gonna have that my exponential becomes
simply 1.
and then basically we turn out having
row 1
that becomes 2 right so alpha
gets deleted by 0 and then you just have
the beta multiplied by
a 1 and then row two automatically is
gonna get
the amplitude of 1.5 right and so
my data points y are going to be simply
points coming from this twice the cosine
of this uniform
simply uniformly sample theta and then
1.5
sine this uniform theta
the collection of all my y's
will give me capital y so capital y is
going to be the collection of all my
sample and here i decided to just use
24 samples so i have 24
different samples from the uniform
distribution
okay and per each of these samples there
will be
one epsilon for the first component and
one epsilon for the second component
all right so what we try to do today
is going to be to learn well to learn
wrong
we are not learning anything we um we
imagine that someone gave us
a already trained already learned
network
we're going to be learning how to
perform inference how we can use a model
to figure out if one point it belongs or
doesn't belong to what was the training
manifold
okay so this is my
training data these are my ys which are
again an ellipse
you can see here the major radii radius
is
two you can see right there are one two
three four boxes each box is 0.5
so this radius here is two and then the
minor radius is gonna have one two
three boxes uh each box is 0.5
and so this is the minor radius of 1.5
when you said there's no input just
what is theta do you consider that an
input or so theta we don't have access
to right
so theta is something we don't see x
could be the input we provide the model
to figure out
at what location we are at that kind of
uh
horn allows us to figure out the
dimension of those
ellipse ellipses but then we theta
here is something we don't have access
to so theta was
is simply a variable which is
uh missing which was used for generating
our data
but we don't have access to so it's a
missing variable it's a missing
input okay so we don't have access okay
all right so let's look at what the
model manifold is so in this case
i'm gonna have a latent input
which is something uh latent mean means
it's missing i don't have access to this
input
still there is some you know potential
you notice here is the same color as
that theta right
anyhow so i have my z z which is uh
i can decide to like take it from zero
to two pi
uh without the so that square bracket
flipped square bracket means
i'm considering a vector that goes from
0 to 2 pi
with 2 pi excluded with a step
you know pi over 24. and so
this one basically is like a line where
there are many points there are uh 40 48
points right
from zero to two pi excluded so this
latent input goes inside a decoder
and then the decoder is going to give me
this y
tilde and y is bold because again it
lives in two dimensions
uh more precisely we're gonna have that
by varying
z over one line y tilde is gonna be
varying
around a uh ellipse okay
on the other side instead we're going to
have these bold y which are my
observations so how do i know these are
observations
because it's uh this circle it's shaded
whereas
those other circles are simply
transparent
the bottom one is a little bit gray
which means i have access to this data
okay
cool so this is how these points look
right the
blue points are the one sample from my
data generation
generated distribution we already
sampled them we have 24
and then here i just decided to plot uh
of these values from like
reconstruction of those latent variables
right such that i can clearly see
what the network thinks uh the the true
manifold
is okay in the second episode
when we are gonna be learning we're
gonna be figuring out how to match
my internal belief the the violet one
with actual the the data we have but
we're not going to be seeing that this
time this time
we already have this model which is
pretty bad since it's not
already matching the data and still
going to be seeing how to use this model
so what what determines the shape of the
red or
orange points is it the alpha and the
beta
uh alpha and beta are determining the
side the
the shape of that blue thing right so
the overall thing it was that horn
uh i showed you before the one that was
spinning and then we decided to slice it
at a specific value of
x right so this is like a cross section
which
gives us this potato the blue potato on
the other side i'm going to be telling
you what is inside the decoder
we have a internal belief for what the
true data manifold is right that's the
net network
that the model believe about the uh
you know the the how the data is
supposed to look
okay let me let me show you in the next
slide a little bit
more information so maybe we can get uh
you know sync so here
we're going to be looking at this energy
function
so what is this energy function so this
energy function
it's um something that tells me
what is the compatibility between this y
tilde and y the blue y right
and so basically in this case here
measures the distance between
my given training sample and my
reconstruction my given my best guess
about what i think it should be the real
data point
so let's give more context here right so
my
energy e function of my
y data point and my latent variable z
it's gonna be the sum of the square
euclidean distances of the two
components
so we have component one of the y minus
component one of this g which is our
decoder
function of z squared and then we have
the other one is going to be y2 minus
g2 which is the second component of this
output of the decoder
squared and this importantly
uh happens for every y we pick
from capital y so in this case
we have 24 different
e's right so we can index 24 different
e's
based on the specific why you pick
more about this in the next slide so
what is this decoder so this decoder is
a little bit
cooked as in you know i know what is the
data generating
uh process so i can put inside the g
what is quite
uh you know align with what i think you
know
it's a very good guess about how
the output should look uh so my g
which is a two component function g one
g two
maps uh the real line to this r2
and therefore it maps my z into these
two components which are going to be w1
cosine cosine of z and then the second
component is going to be w2 because
the sine of z to notice here
the only parameters we have available
in this network in this decoder are w1
and w2
okay cosine x and sine z
sorry cosine z and sine z are you know
knowledge a priori you know i know
already and i
put there my best guess for that
and so again this network has two
parameters nevertheless
with two parameters we can still do many
things
so again stress once again uh this e
happens to exist for any peak
of y in this set of all y's
so let's put uh this e on on the top
here just so i can
i can clear the screen below and so
now i show you all 24
energies we have how do we
how do i get this stuff right so these
energies are coming from the fact that i
pick
a specific y so the first one i pick
y prime which is like my peak of y is
going to be the first
of my training sample and therefore i
can call
the first energy my e1 right so i can
index them
right now since i have you know a
discrete number of training samples
i have a discrete number of energies in
this case
so this is my e1 and then the last one
on the row is going to be in the one
associated to the sixth
sample of my training sample my training
set
and therefore i have my e6
uh if we go down until the last row
we're gonna be
seeing uh i'm gonna be picking the 19th
sample from my training set and then i'm
going to have this e 19 over there
and finally if i pick my y prime
being the last the 24th example then
i'll be
ending up with the e24 on the x axis
of each of these little cells you're
going to be having z
so each of these e's know e 1 e 2 e 3
e until 24 are functions
of my z latent variable which is
spanning as we said before
zero to two pi in this uh drawing here i
just have them
separated by uh pi over 12. so i have
nice
separation for drawing this function
so moreover the range of this energy
in this case is going to be 0 to 12 and
we are we're going to be computing these
values in a
just in a short moment such that we can
better understand
what the heck i'm talking about right so
again until yesterday i had no clue
about what these were okay so i am
very new to this topic as well and
therefore we are
exploring together what is this jungle
of very
funny weird wiggly functions okay
we are gonna start by cherry picking two
of them
uh for example the e23
the e23 looks pretty you know
kind of okay it looks very uh
mostly smooth and i think it looks like
uh
you know even convex in the in the
central part
and then i'm gonna be of course if i
pick the nice one and smooth one i'm
gonna be also picking some weird stuff
like like the the double wiggly the one
which
is wiggling yeah but as i said let's
start with
ease and let's start with the with a
simple version okay so far everything is
all right no one is writing anything on
the chat and
you know sean just asked a few questions
so so far we are
all on board or i lost some of you
no yeah so so basically like this square
would be y23 and then the x-axis is
showing
as you vary z you're going to be
evaluating this e
y 23 and z yeah yeah this is the e23 the
the one i
show you right now great the lecture's
going
great i'm understanding as well okay
okay that's fantastic
okay so let's look at this first
example on this kind of u shape so how
does
this u shape uh arise right
and so this is the current configuration
we have y prime is going to be the 23rd
example from my training
set which is refigured here by that
green x on the right hand side okay
so over here whenever i start
my z my z and i start with z equals zero
it actually turns out that z zero
corresponds
to this location over here so if i send
z
equals zero inside the decoder i'm gonna
get a point over here
why is that oh because simply the w1
we just randomly generated is a negative
number
and so this uh this size over here from
zero like this the point from here to
here this is my w1
and instead w2 is going to be a positive
number over here
so whenever we have z equals 0 you're
going to have that the cosine of
0 is going to be equal to 1 so it
becomes 1 multiplied by
a negative number i go down here and
then
0 sine of zero is going to be zero so
you're gonna be you're gonna be on the x
axis
so over here this is gonna be my initial
point
uh how far is this point from the green
x
let's count so we have one two boxes
three four boxes five six
six boxes and seven right so
two boxes are one right so seven
boxes means we have three and a half
right
so if i count it correctly one two three
three and a half so the distance between
this point
over here and the green guy over here
it's roughly
three and a half now if you take three
and a half
and you square it you get
yeah you guess it's right it's 12 right
and that's why we get this point over
here
you don't trust me take out the
calculator and check how much is 3.5
squared
okay anyhow so that's why we start
at this location uh here 12 right
as we keep uh increasing z and we go
from
zero to pi half we end up at this
location over here
and then as we keep going until pi
you're gonna get and ending up in this
location over here
and as you can tell uh pi
you're gonna be at one square away from
this green boy and so one square is
gonna be
0.5 0.5 square is 0.25
and therefore the height of this red
curve
at this location over here it's 0.25
very close to zero okay and then
we still keep cranking up that z and we
go to
three three half pi and then you keep
going up to two pi right and two pi
we're gonna be basically getting up to
the same location
where we started okay and then if you
keep going you're gonna repeat this one
it's gonna be going up and down
up and down up and down all right all
right so this looks pretty
okay i think no no no crazy stuff but
then we saw the other one was kind of
wiggly right what happened there so
instead of using the y
23 we're going to be using now the y10
which is this
thing right like a signature like yarn
signature all right
so what happened here so in this case
our
y prime which is the peak we have
from my possible wise is this guy over
here the top
x over here and again as i told you
before whenever z
is equal to 0 we start at this location
over here
so if you have understood what i'm
talking about and now we're going to be
doing an exercise such that you answer
me
can you tell me what is the distance
between this location over here
and this point over here so question for
the people at home
can anyone tell me what is the length
of this segment i just
draw and i'm
okay 1.5 times 1.4
which is square root of 2. yes so
that's correct and if you square it
you're gonna have what
is going to be 1.5 times 1.5 times 2
right i just squared so you said 1.5
times square root of 2. i'm just
squaring everything so we're going to
get
1.5 squared times 2. so 1.5 times 2 it's
and 3 times 1.4 1.5 is 4.5 right
and so we can determine that my initial
energy
which is the square length of this
segment
is going to be 4.5 which is exactly what
this initial value over here is okay so
this point over here
it's 4.5 um
can you just repeat why you know that
z equals zero corresponds to the
leftmost point
yes so i know that uh this is because i
checked the code
i know that my w1 it's um
it's equal to something uh that is
uh minus 1.5 right
something like that minus one
point five
okay and then we have the w tool
and i'm drawing with the touchpad so
it's crazy
uh this is 0.3
0.4 something like that
zero point let's say four
that looks like a one but okay
okay believe me it's a four okay when we
go pi
half we are roughly uh one unit
away from this point so one square is
going to be roughly one
right i mean some something roughly one
square is gonna still be
there so this height over here is gonna
be one
and then we climb up to this location
over here
uh in this location over here
we should basically get the same
point over here so then over
here we're going to get a similar value
a little bit smaller and then we
oh what happened here so when we go to
three
three half pi we actually are
at this location over here and we have
another minimum right
what happened here so basically you had
this point is
closer to my green guy than
a point over here right and so in this
case
this function here this energy has a
local minima
which is happening at three three half
pi at this location over here
all right cool uh let's go back to the
arrow
okay so now we determine that this
height was 4.5
this was one and then this something we
can figure this is gonna be like two
square this is gonna be four okay
okay so what happened now oh all this
stuff is still here
okay clean all right free energy so what
is this free energy
so we're gonna figure that out right now
so the free energy
um actually this is the zero temperature
limit of the free energy
it's going to be simply the mean minimum
value of this
e function with respect to z
so we can compute this
z check which is gonna be equal
we can define it as being the arc mean
of this energy function
uh with respect to z why the check
well because the check is pointing
downwards right so whenever i minimize
my energy i found the location that is
the lowest one
and theref that's why i'm gonna put the
check means means
that z is the location where the uh
the energy is the lowest okay
um and how do can we find that set right
so
if um if z it's basically
uh discrete like let's say we have like
k means
uh we have we can do exhaustive search
we can check every z
we have otherwise we can use
techniques like gradient based
techniques such as
gradient descent and keep
like pay attention i didn't say
stochastic gradient descent
because here we are not doing any
stochastic something right
uh e is a function of what we know
everything uh when we do stochastic a in
the same we are minimizing that
loss function which is expressed as an
average of those pair
sample loss functions right here instead
we are minimizing
this specific value of e there is no
average so it's not stochastic
and therefore you're going to be using
you can use algorithms such that
conjugate gradient
line search lbf gs and so on okay
so let's look at and let's figure out
what is this
free energy right how it works so given
that we have defined this
uh z check this uh free energy
the the zero limit for the free energy
is going to simply be this
energy e computed in the location of my
z
check so let's visualize here
this uh e uh so this
e10 all the energy for the sample when i
pick the sample pen
i initialize my latent variable z
tilde the orange one with some volume
and then i'm gonna be running a gradient
base method for
minimization therefore i end up in the
blue location which is my z
check and it's blue because it's cold so
it's like low
i usually think about this energy as
being like a temperature right
i mean if you multiply by the boltzmann
boltzmann constant no k
kt uh you're gonna get like the some
energy right
so energy and temperature are very uh
very closely related
um and so again i use the the blue to
show you that is low
and cold and so at that location that z
check the yeah at that location we
reached the minimum
of this energy and that is my uh
free energy the zero limit for the free
energy
cool cool cool so so in practice
this could depend on the initialization
then
oh yeah oh yeah so well
yeah the initialization uh so your
algorithm
will screw up depending on the
initialization for sure
so i can show you later on that lbfgs
actually gets the wrong
minimum but nevertheless the free energy
is the global minimum right
so i'm telling you here that
the value the minimum value of e is the
free energy
if we don't get there because we don't
know how to get there and then
it's a different issue right so it's not
dependent on the initialization
uh the initialization will make
your algorithm more or less likely to
converge to the actual
correct solution all right
so what happens here
so in this case here we have uh the blue
points are my points from the training
distribution
the tilde one are you know same poles
from my distrib from my model
then my y prime is the peak i have
chosen right so this is my 10th item in
the training set
then my z-tilde which is the initialized
the value i initialize z with if i send
it through the
decoder i showed you before it's going
to generate this point
here this this location over here
then i can run some some some
minimization algorithm
and then you end up in that location the
blue location and the blue x
is going to be the you know decoded
version of the z
check which is the closest item to this
green boy over here so
why are we doing this stuff here how can
we use this model what we use
can you what can we use this model for
so we can think about
you know if we have someone has trained
this model and has given
that to us we can potentially
find what is the closest value
in our possible you know
set of all possible values we can
generate which is the closest
to your sample but so we can use this
for performing denoising for example so
if i have an image which is corrupted
which is going to be there for far from
my manifold the model manifold
then i can ask my model hey model can
you tell me what
is the latent which is gonna give you
the uh decoded version the decoded
uh item here which is the closest as
possible to the
uh image i'm looking at and then
potentially we could just
pick this value over here as you know uh
cleaned up version
of my uh corrupted input
what is the energy uh the free energy
the free energy now
it's simply the square distance between
the green point
and the blue x right so if you take this
location these two boxes which is
basically one
one square which is rough again one is
going to be
the free energy corresponding to this x
over here okay so every x every location
here in the training manifold will have
a
free energy which is determining what is
the
distance to the the what is the closest
distance to the manifold
okay so you can see in this case
that let's say uh our model is well
trained
we can tell that this location over here
has much
a much lower free energy than a point
over here
and so these points could be more likely
coming from
these you know uh could be compatible
with what this model has been trained on
or like we show in this case this model
is definitely
not well trained uh so what do you mean
by well trained
uh in this case here just for you know
pedagogical
uh sake i didn't train fully in this
model
such that there are errors in ideally
those purple points should be exactly
matching those blue points and that
would be you know
a well-trained model which is capturing
all the dependencies
between those y variables and this is
again one cross section
right of that horn this is a not well
trained
model which means i stopped training
after
a few epochs and therefore the model
tried to get there but it didn't quite
manage to get yet there
uh we can think about that
or we can think about this is a
well-trained model so you actually learn
properly and then these points here are
much further away
so by computing the free energy of these
points you can have like a
measure of how far they are from the
learned distribution okay
all right so let's move on and let's
look now instead
of the the 23rd right and the 23rd u
shape and so in this case instead oh
it's much easier we just have a global
minimum and a global maximum
so there is a question if this were
for denoising and the model was trained
to the point
where the t-points were on top of the
till points
wouldn't it be not do any denoising
so i believe that you're saying if the
till points are far away from the
uh from the from the purple one right so
that would mean that the model would
would be not well trained right so if we
yeah if these blue points were like up
here and all of them would have been you
know
uh closer to some point over over here
that means that this model is bad is
badly trained right
so again today we don't talk about
training so this is simply what has been
given to us
and we just play uh with what we have
and try to figure out
what this energy and what is free energy
mean
okay so this is how to use this stuff
rather than
to learn this stuff learning next time
it's enough to understand how to use
this trust me
all right so let's figure out what's
going on with this u
shape so the u shape instead comes from
this
kind of example here so again here
we initialize to the location in
orange and then by running some you know
gradient based method or whatever
minimization process
we find these blue x which is my z
check so we go from the z tilde which is
the initialized
uh value for my latent to this z check
which is the
value at which i find the minimum
for my uh energy
since this is periodic i'm going to show
you just on the next repetition so i
don't clutter too much the chart
and this came from this configuration
over here
we start with these training points uh
these are points from
you know i just sampled them from my
mother
my peak was this green over here
and in this case perhaps i can tell that
the model
we initialized the the latent with the
orange
and then he actually went a little bit
too much i think he didn't choose
the exact best right so this is like a
bit it overshoot a little bit i think uh
anyhow
this over free energy of this location
here
is going to be 0.25 right 0.5 square
cool cool cool so what's left to show
you
well just a few more things but we are
almost finished
and then i'm looking for all your
questions because i
i i really i really know you have
questions i i have questions
so let's in this case compute the free
energy
for every location i show you in this
grid
what does computing the free energy for
every location means
so just for sake of you know
clarity i'm gonna just repeat myself uh
because i like to listen
or to talk right so i i like to talk so
uh so let's let's select in
in green here let's say i'm picking this
sample over here as my first location
so given that location there i'm gonna
be picking a
orange do we have orange there is no
orange okay i have to pick red
sorry so let's say i initialize
my my latent variable such that
the g the decoded version of the
z tilde is this point over here then we
run
our minimization process to perform
inference right to find out what is that
check so whenever we
find z check that process is called
inference
given an energy given a sample
y not given a location y i do inference
to figure out
what was the most likely latent variable
missing variable that generated that
point over there
so inference again means we are doing
minimization
and therefore we are moving around our
model manifold until i get to this
location over here
what is this location over there this
location is the location that is the
closest to my
uh sample y that i picked
therefore what is my free energy so my
free energy is going to be simply the
square
distance from this green guy
and the red one right so this segment
over here
squared is going to be the free energy
of this point over here
so question from for you how do
the free energy of the point on top left
compares
with the energy of
[Music]
the point i circle in yellow over here
which one is larger which one is smaller
and
where where is my z check for the second
example
green is larger yes green is larger
because this distance here
square it's gonna be much larger than
the which distance so similarly
if we initialize you know with luck and
we run great in
the descent like gradient based methods
we may end up in a location that is over
here
and therefore the free energy is going
to be the square distance between that
point
and that point here so definitely this
point would be much larger
uh the energy free energy with respect
to this point
so some other question someone can make
is gonna be uh
how far is the green point from my
distribution right how how far is the
green point from my
learned distribution and the learn
distribution here is represented by the
those blue points right so you can tell
that that point in the top left
it's it's going to have a higher energy
so it's further away it's
less compatible with you know
uh with respect to the other guy right
all right so we are almost almost done
here
so let's to make like some exercise
pay attention to those five values right
so i'm picking that
uh row there just below the x axis and
i'm picking the first
and then the fourth uh and so on right
example and so i'm going to be plotting
now
these energy functions they look pretty
much
like this so for the
blue one as you can expect we extend
up to 20 and then we go
down to 2.5 roughly 20 is going to be in
this location like the distance between
this point and this further point away
here
squared and then instead 2.5 square is
going to be
you know this distance here square
similarly you're gonna have you know an
energy function for the red one
for the purple green and orange
then given that i compute all these
values for the energy
i can now compute what is the free
energy so the free energy
instead of being a function is going to
be a
value when i pick a specific location
right so it's no longer a function of
the latent whenever we compute the free
energy
the latent disappears and i
get that z check which is the optimal
latent on the latent that is
the most likely giving me uh
that that point so here we have that the
z check for the blue curve happens over
here similarly the z check for the
orange green and purple and red
are happening in these locations uh
there
for sure we could have ended up caught
in this local minimum right that
definitely could be a pitfall of you
know
of using some gradient-based methods
so question now for the audience
i'm removing everything what is f
infinity so how many dimensions does
this stuff okay
can someone remind me this right so can
someone tell me what is the domain and
the image
of these function on the chart
where does f infinity live
[Music]
anyone run sir is anyone listening
hello okay so y
is uh on r24 yeah but that's
uh there is just an r i don't know what
just r means um
the capital y is 20
capital y has 24 items each item in
capital y
are two dimensional right so y is a
matrix but i'm not asking the capital y
i'm asking capital f
infinity right so capital f infinity is
uh someone mentioned here it's
definitely a real value
uh in our case is actually positively
non-negatively
value right because it's a it's a square
sum of squares
and the domain instead what is the
domain of capital f
the domain is going to be the uh the
basically the where y uh
the bold y belongs to no so the ball y
it's a vector in two dimensions so
that's gonna be r two right so again
these f
are scalar values so i'm gonna be
representing the different intensities
of this
scalar value with this color bar here
i will represent in a violet very dark
maybe not even able to see in this free
energy
uh equals zero then in aqua
i'm gonna be representing this zero
temperature limit
uh free energy for uh equal one and then
everything that is above and beyond the
value two
is going to be yellow and so this is
how that grid looks
okay so each location in that grid here
and i show you before and those green
points have a
free energy which is here represented by
this color
in this location over here in the bottom
side you can see it's yellow
which means it has a free energy which
is
equal or larger than 2. moreover
those arrows are pointing
are the gradient right so these are
pointing in the direction of maximum
uh ascend as we move closer
to the uh this region here you're gonna
get
finally you're gonna see some colors and
here you can tell the free energy is
getting lower lower lower
until we hit the location where this
reconstruction happen
which is the location the region where
my free energy is zero
when we train this modern we try to get
this zero energy level to be matching
the location of these blue points of
course
as you can tell this model is very
poorly trained
and therefore this energy surface is not
well matching my training point it's
getting close but it's not yet there
so next time we're gonna see how to
stretch this energy
such that it's gonna be you know nicely
fitting on these blue points okay
uh why is the energy surface single
value
so the energy surface
which is the value of f infinity right
and f infinity is the minimum of my
energy so
energy the capital e it's a function
over all possible latent but then
given that we have this function we're
going to find what is the minimum value
minimum value that this energy can take
that minimum value
is the uh zero temperature limit
of the free energy which is this f
infinity okay and so e
y z is a function of y and z
but then whenever we take out the z with
the minimization
we get this f which is going to be a
function
of y right so every time i move across
the y space here we have y1 and y2 the
two components
you're gonna have that f will have you
know larger than two larger than two
blah blah blah then
1.75 1.50 and so on lower values until
we get
f roughly zero and then actually it
increases a little bit
so maybe next time i also gonna show you
this chart uh in a 3d version also
rotating
i didn't have time to do that um
did i answer your question is it clear
why this
energy function is single value like as
in a scalar value right you mean single
value
am i understanding the question
correctly
but we have 24 y's so the
capital the y's are these blue points
right now my y's i'm using
are this one so they're not 24 there are
so if you count from here let me go a
bit larger i can see
so here we have blah blah blah 12
and 12 here plus one we have 25
and then here we had eight
and eight sixteen plus one seventeen so
right now we have 17 times 25
i don't know how much it is someone can
compute okay google how much is 17 times
okay she's not listening oh 120
425 uh there you go
so right now we have 425
points right so we have 424
24 425 energy functions
of which function of y so
given that i pick a y i have an energy
function those are functions in z
given that you pick the minimum value of
this energy function that's going to be
your free energy
for a specific y so you remove that
latent variable so we have
an internal possible way of spending our
uh manifold right so you want to think
about this as you know
you have like uh your potato in your
model like your model thinks about the
data is
distributed as this kind of shape and
then
your latent variable allows you to go
all around this potato
so right now if you add if you ask me oh
is this
point here on your manifold or not so if
this point is on my manifold
i know that by going around my manifold
and find out if
oh i get there right and so if
the free energy of that point is zero
therefore it means that that point you
are asking me about
leaves on the manifold that the model
has learned
if your free energy is not zero then
it's gonna be simply
equal to the quadratic uh euclidean
distance
from that location from your point and
my
manifold right did i answer the question
yeah okay uh more questions for me
oh was everything clear i i this stuff i
really just digested it uh like in the
past
30 hours so again i might not have done
a very good job
let's see how do we choose a function to
represent the data manifold
in this case it seemed like we chose a
ellipse based on the data but how about
other scenarios yeah definitely uh
there is a lot of you know research
going in uh
architectures right network
architectures so
but again uh right now yeah we we chose
that
next time i'm gonna be trying to learn
the level of compatibility
like i'm gonna try to learn this energy
for the x y
z the the triple right and so
we're gonna be just using neural nets
right even the sine and cosine
you can somehow approximate them with a
few layers right so instead of having
these
uh z function uh the g function
over here instead of having this very
simple thing
we can think about having you know a few
layers of a neural net right
so you can still use a few layers of a
neural net
but you're not going to be using the
neural net to do vector
vector mapping you're going to be using
a neural net to do
a bunch of vectors to scalars right
so bunch of vectors to scalars is going
to be this
energy-based you know way of thinking
about things
uh because again how do you
let's say you want to translate
something from one language to another
language right
so i have one sentence but i may
translate that sentence
in different ways in another language
right so how do you train this you
cannot really say
i do soft marks because first of all
there is an infinite number
of sentences so you can't do that
but then there might be even multiple
sentences that are correctly associated
to your first sentence
so this energy based model allow you to
end up with a
score scoring mechanism which is this
energy
which is telling you how compatible are
points right so here x y and z are all
interchangeable
given one i can find the other right so
if i have the energy
if my model learned the energy i can
find x given y
i can find y given z i can find z given
x i can find
all kind of combination those x y z i
don't even have to write them x y and z
i can just write all the components
right and then i can
as long as my model learns that right it
learns all the
uh how do you call them um interactions
that
exist in my data that's why uh jan likes
them so much and they're super powerful
because they don't make too many
assumptions i think
uh did i okay i answer your question uh
we are over time so i think
this lesson was kind of
fine i don't know you had to tell me
because i really don't know
i hope you like this yeah that was great
okay because people are very
quiet today i wanted to make also a
notebook but then the notebook is really
ugly
because i use the notebook to make very
pretty
visualization but the code is really
ugly maybe next time
i can share with you a cleanup version
of the notebook for
pedagogical purpose right and especially
going to be
showing you this network which doesn't
have an input doesn't have a forward
function
which is so funny uh and then we're
gonna be learning perhaps
what is the free energy without this
beta that goes to
um to infinity and we're gonna be
learning how to do
learning okay so today again we just
learned so let me get to the beginning
so we can end up
here so today we talk about inference
okay
we do inference by doing minimization of
an energy function
learning is something we're going to be
talking about next time they don't they
don't
they don't have anything to share well
it's two different topics right
next time the other one and then the
other part so it was inference for
latent
variable energy based model which allow
you to capture
this multi multi modality of you know
multi
multi modality of coexistence of things
right you can you don't have simply
vector to vector you have
one too many options right and then we
talk about
uh we talk about this stuff here now
and how we can possibly try to learn
this combination of x y uh x y
combination right
uh so there's a question so minimizing
energy regarding to
train manifold basically means denoising
uh i think you can think about that as
yeah in that way
so the real manifold
okay depends which one is the real
manifold right so if the model
has learned the the real manifold then
you know by minimizing the energy
you can find what is the denoised
version of your input
another option you have to denoise this
stuff is going to be if you find
yourself here
you can compute this energy you can
follow the gradient and then here you
can recompute the energy
you can still go and follow the energy
the gradient so you can end up boom
down on the manifold right so you can
make little steps so you can just go
uh you know you can find out where to go
or you can use the
uh you know the z check
to find out what is the uh best
approximation of your point over here
right
okay all right so that was it um thank
you for listening you have a nice
evening
i see on friday i feel free to ask jan
questions about this
uh this this practicum he he was you
know
helping a lot as well right have a good
night
bye bye
so how can you get more out of this
lesson today
comprehension if something was not yet
clear
you should really ask me uh anything in
the comment section below okay
i will answer every comment that you
write over there
news if you would like to keep up with
everything i post online you should
check
my twitter account under alph cnz
if you also would like youtube to notify
about you the latest
videos i upload then press that
subscribe button and turn on the
notification bell
such that you're not going to be missing
any content if you like this video
put a like on it it means a lot to me
searching we have a companion website
where you can find each and every video
transcribed
by students that volunteered for example
here
you can see this lesson transcribed
as you can tell the titles are links
which are
redirecting you to the correct section
in the video
so here we have this lesson transcribed
to you in english moreover
not only english is available as you can
tell here there is the
english flag you can go up on top for
example and i show you
the home page here you can find that
many languages are available arabic
spanish version
french italian japanese korean russian
turkish
and chinese and more are coming if you
would like to contribute and add your
own language
don't hesitate to contact me on twitter
or by email
this is the language part moreover it
really really helps
if you implement things that we cover in
class
with file torch and you know a notebook
perhaps
in some patient today class didn't have
a companion notebook
but nevertheless i would really
recommend you to
try to put together a few trials
yourself such that you can test your
knowledge
finally if you find any bug in the
previous notebooks
in the website anywhere you're really
encouraged to
point them out on github or if you find
yourself inclined
you can also send a pull request such
that you can be an official contributor
to this project
and don't forget to like share and
subscribe
bye bye
you